ARGHYA CHATTERJEE



□ arghyame20buet@gmail.com

https://arghyachatterjee.github.io

https://github.com/ArghyaChatterjee

A robotics and machine learning researcher experienced in applying Deep Learning, Edge & Cloud Computing in Computer Vision for Object Detection, Segmentation & Localization, Advanced Perception based SLAM for Localization, Mapping, Metric & Semantic understanding of the environment, Control theory & Deep Reinforcement Learning for risk aware autonomous robotic exploration in perceptually degraded environments and Swarm Intelligence for multirobot collaboration & rapid exploration in outer space to help take better decision for humans.

EDUCATION

Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Degree: BSc. in Mechanical Engineering Feb 2015 - Sept 2019

CGPA: 3.14/4.00

Khulna Public College, Khulna, Bangladesh

Degree: HSC in Science Jul 2012 - Aug 2014 GPA: 5.00/5.00 Class Position: 1st/60

Khulna Bidyut Kendra Secondary School, Khulna, Bangladesh

Degree: SSC in Science Jan 2010 - May 2012 GPA: 5.00/5.00 Class Position: 1st/60

RESEARCH & PROJECT EXPERIENCE

Advisor & Robotics Engineer, Lotus Robotics

Oct 2021 - Present Newyork, USA

Research Engineer for ROS based Autonomous Robotics Projects Project Coordinator: Mansurul Haque

Responsibilities:

Developing Autonomous UGVs for GPS guided delivery missions.

- Developing Autonomous UGVs for Warehouse Security, Lawn Mowing & Floor Scrubbing.
- Building Autonomous UAVs for agriculture & surveying.
- Team Member, Team CoSTAR of NASA JPL

Iul 2020 - Sep 2021

California, USA

DARPA organized SubT Challenge

Perception Team Supervisors: Dr. B. Morrell (NASA JPL) & Prof. L. Carlone (MIT)

Responsibilities:

- Built Advanced perceptive sensor based multi-robot SLAM algorithm (LOCUS & LAMP) and analyzed efficiency, accuracy & robustness with SOTA algorithms.
- Developed Object detection & localization capability for robots like Spot, Husky, Rollercopter & UAV with advanced perceptive sensors as part of NeBula autonomy Solution.
- Team Supervisor & Educator, STEMX 365

Jan 2020 - Present

JAXA (& NASA) org. Kibo-Astrobee ISS Robot Programming Challenge International Project Coordinator: Mizanul H. Chowdhury (MIT)

Tokyo, Japan

Responsibilities:

- Helped in Developing Algorithms for Autonomously operate Astrobee (A free flying robot) inside ISS avoiding obstacles, following way points and detecting QR & AR Tag.
- Educated students about ISS & How Astrobee is going to help astronauts automate tasks.
- Research Assistant at Mars Rover Lab (MRL), BUET

Oct 2019 - Sept 2020

Project Researcher, Advisor & Instructor for URC, ERC, IPASC & KRPC

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Supervisor: Dr. Md. Ashigur Rahman (BUET)

Responsibilities:

- Carried out research on Autonomous Navigation Based on GPS, SLAM & Object Detection and Plan Path accordingly for Safe Exploration of Rovers on Rough Terrains, Caves and Mineral Ores of Earth and Mars.
- Software Team Leader & Member, Team Interplanetar ESA organized ERC & Mars Society organized URC Supervisor: Dr. Md. Ashigur Rahman (BUET)

Jun 2017 - Sep 2019

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Responsibilities:

• Lead Software Group & Built a GPS Guided Autonomous Mars Rover Mission & On-board Object Detection for University Rover Challenge (URC) and Way-point Based Autonomous Mars Rover Mission & On-board AR Tag Detection for European Rover Challenge (ERC).

Researcher & Collaborator at Department of ME, BUET

Mar 2018 – Apr 2019 Dhaka, Bangladesh

Supervisors: Dr. Maglub Al Nur (BUET) and Dr. Muhammad Abir (MIT)

Responsibilities:

Undergraduate Thesis

• Investigated Pool Boiling IR Images of MIT's Nuclear Reactor Lab Computationally for Segmentation of Dry Spots Automatically and Evaluated Performance of Traditional Image Processing and Deep Neural Networks in Quantifying Dry Area Segments.

• Team Leader, Team Octatron

Mar 2017 - Feb 2018

Undergraduate Project Dhaka, Bangladesh

Supervisors: Dr. M.A. Rashid Sarkar and Musanna Galib (BUET)

Responsibilities:

• Lead a Team & Built a Fire and Flood Fighter Octocopter (UAV) for Extinguishing Fire in Fire Affected Buildings and Distributing Flood Reliefs to people in Flood Affected Zones.

• Researcher & Technical Leader, Team Out of the Box

Jan 2017 - May 2017

Microsoft BD Internship Project

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Supervisors: Sonia B. Kabir and Ashikur Rahman (Microsoft)

Responsibilities:

• Lead a Team & Built a Mobile Application for Earlier Screening of Particular Disability in Children Using Microsoft Products like Azure Cloud Platform and Bing Maps Server.

• Team Leader, Team Igniters

Jul 2016 - Feb 2017 Dhaka, Bangladesh

Undergraduate Project

Supervisors: Dr. M.A. Rashid Sarkar and Dr. A. B. M. Alim Al Islam (BUET)

Responsibilities:

• Lead a Team and Built a Hand Wearable Solar Powered Obstacle Detection and Safe Navigation Device for Blind People in Low Cost.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

• BUET Mars Rover Robotics Team
Teaching Assistant at Mars Rover Lab (MRL), BUET

• JAXA org. Kibo Astrobee ISS Robot Prog. Challenge Educator & Instructor of Teams from Bangladesh, STEMX 365

• National Space Carnival & Camp Instructor & Academic Coordinator f

Instructor & Academic Coordinator for Workshops & Camps

Bangladesh Astronomical Society
Instructor for Workshops & Seminars

Oct 2020 - Present Dhaka, Bangladesh

Jan 2020 - Present Dhaka, Bangladesh

Sep 2019 - Jun 2020 Dhaka, Bangladesh

Mar 2017 – Apr 2019 Dhaka, Bangladesh

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Lotus Robotics

Oct 2021 – Present

Advisor & Robotics Engineer

Newyork, USA

Activities: Working on Autonomous UGVs for GPS guided delivery missions, Warehouse Security, Lawn Mowing & Floor Scrubbing and UAVs for agriculture & surveying.

• Bangladesh Astronomy Research Collaboration (BARC)
Advisor & Fellow Member

Jan 2020 – Present

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Activities: Give advice on research activities & how the organization should operate.

• Youthprenuer Network (A Social Welfare Organization)

Jun 2019 - Jun 2020

Head of STEM Education & Development

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Activities: Instructed, Organized and Lead Projects, Workshops, Olympiads and Camps in Educational Institutions to Promote STEM Education in Bangladesh.

American Astronomical Society

Apr 2018 - Mar 2020

Country Collaborator & Member

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Activities: Celebrated International Astronomical Events in Bangladesh and Reported to Proper AAS Authority for Publishing on their Magazines.

PUBLICATIONS

- Matteo Palieri, Benjamin Morrell, Abhishek Thakur, Kamak Ebadi, Jeremy Nash, Arghya Chatterjee, Christoforos Kanellakis, Luca Carlone, Cataldo Guaragnella, Ali-akbar Aghamohammadi, "LOCUS: A Multi-Sensor Lidar-Centric Solution for High-Precision Odometry and 3D Mapping in Real-Time," IEEE Robotics & Automation Letters Journal, 2020, vol: 6/2, pp. 421-428.
- Arghya Chatterjee, M. Galib and M. A. R. Sarkar, "Application of Arduino in designing modern electromechanical laboratory," 2017 IEEE International Conference on Power, Control, Signals and Instrumentation Engineering (ICPCSI), Chennai, 2017, pp. 222-225.
- Arghya Chatterjee, S. Dutta, P. Sarkar and A. B. M. A. A. Islam, "Obstacle Detector for Blind People with Low Cost (Poster Presentation)," Proceedings of 2017 International Conference on Networking, Systems and Security (NSysS), Dhaka, 2017.

INTERNSHIPS & TRAININGS

•	Microsoft Bangladesh Limited	Jan 2017 - May 2017
	Internship Project: Disabling Disability through Microsoft Products	Dhaka, Bangladesh
•	Khulna Power Company Limited	Oct 2018 - Oct 2018
	Training: Power Plant Visit & Industrial Attachment (3 weeks)	Khulna, Bangladesh

SKILL SETS

- **Prg. Language:** Python, C++, C#, Arduino, Java, Java S, HTML, PHP, CSS, & LATEX.
- Framework & OS: ROS, ROS2, OpenCV, PCL, Nvidia Isaac SDK, Keras, TensorFlow, PyTorch, Caffe, CUDA, OpenGL, Kubernetes, .NET, Django, Linux, Mac, Windows & Android.
- **Software & Tool:** Git, Github, Gitlab, Docker, MIPAR, Solidworks, Ansys, PLC, Blender, Unity & UE 4, Verge3D, Carla Simulator, Microsoft Airsim, Deeplab, OpenPose3D, Meshroom, Meshlab, CloudCompare, Open3D, OpenDroneMap, OpenSpace, Photoshop, Kdenlive & MS Office Family.
- **IDE, Compiler & Text Editor:** CodeBlocks, Microsoft Visual Studio, MATLAB, Atom, Jupiter Notebook, PyCharm, Android Studio, Nodejs, IntelliJ IDEA,VS Code & Notepad++.
- Cloud Platform: AWS Compute, AWS RoboMaker & Storage, GCP, Google Colab.
- Hardware: GPS (RTK), IMU, VLP-16 (3D) & RPLidar (2D) LIDAR, Intel Realsense D200 & 400 series RGBD & L515 Lidar Camera, ZED 3D Camera, Microsoft Kinect Camera, Nvidia Jetson & Intel NUC Boards, Arduino & Raspberry PI Boards, Pixhawk, Ardupilot, VESC, BLDC motor, Nvidia AMD GTX Boards & Oculus Rift S VR Headset.
- Language Proficiency: Bangla, English & Hindi.

AWARDS, HONORS & SCHOLARSHIPS

•	5th Worldwide in Final Round of DARPA SubT Challenge	Sep 2021
	Awarded to Team CoSTAR of NASA JPL for competing in the final round	Kentucky, USA
•	Special Grant from ICT Division (Ministry) of Bangladesh	Feb 2020
	Awarded to BUET Mars Rover Lab (MRL) for outstanding performance in robotics	Dhaka, BD
•	Gold Medalist from Duke of Edinburgh International Foundation	Dec 2019
	Awarded for Outstanding Extra-curricular & Service to the Society	London, UK
•	2nd in Asia & 16th Internationally in European Mars Rover Challenge	Sep 2019
	Organized by European Space Foundation (ESF) & European Space Agency (ESA)	Kielce, Poland
•	Special Fund & Grant from BUET Alumni Association Trust	Jul 2019
	Awarded to Team Interplanetar of BUET MRL for competition & robotics research	Dhaka, BD
•	Finalist in IEEE SS12 International Project Competition & Maker Fair	Jul 2017
	Organized at SS12: Age of Innovation and Maker Fair 2017	Hyderabad, India
•	1st in National Project Show Competition (Senior Category)	May 2017
	Organized at EEE Day, BUET	Dhaka, BD
•	3rd in Inter University Project Show Competition	Apr 2017
	Organized at Mechanical Festival, BUET	Dhaka, BD
•	1st in National Poster Presentation Competition	Mar 2017
	Organized at Robolution, MIST	Dhaka, BD

2nd in Inter University Project Show Competition

Organized at CSE Day, BUET

Nov 2016 Dhaka, BD

1st in All Classes (2002 - 2014)

• Primary at Elizabeth M Primary School (2002-2006) • Junior at Khulna BKS School (2006-2009)

• Secondary at Khulna BKS School (2009-2012)

• H. S. at Khulna Public College (2013-2014)

Govt. Merit Scholarship from Education Board of Bangladesh (2006 - 2019)

• Primary Scholarship (2006-2009)

• Secondary Scholarship (2013-2014)

Olympiad Achievements

• 1 st in Reg. R. of Science Olympiad'14

• 3 rd in Reg. & 10 th in Nat. R. of Astro-Olympiad'13 • 3 rd in Reg. R. of Math Olympiad'14

• Junior Scholarship (2010-2012)

• H. Secondary Scholarship (2015-2019)

• 1 st in Reg. R. of Zoology Olympiad'14

CERTIFICATIONS (COURSERA)

Machine Learning by Stanford University, Feb 2018.

Deep Learning Specialization (5 course) by Deeplearning.ai, Sept 2018.

Robotics Specialization (6 course) by University of Pennsylvania (UPenn), Sept 2021.

Modern Robotics: Mechanics, Planning & Control Specialization by Northwestern Uni, May 2021.

Control of Mobile Robots by Georgia Institute of Technology, May 2020.

Image & Video Processing by Duke University, Nov 2018.

Intro to Satellite Communications by Institut Mines - Télécom, May 2019.

Wireless Communications for Everybody by Yonsei University, Dec 2018.

LEADERSHIPS

Head of STEM Education & Development

Software Team Lead

Technical Lead of Internship Project

President (Senior Rover Mate)

President

Youthprenuer Network Team Interplanetar, BUET Microsoft BD

BUET Rover Scout Group

Satyen Bose Science Club, BUET

VOLUNTEERING

Sceptre (Poverty Alleviation Organization)

Jan 2015 - Present

Activities: Org. free medical camps & distribute dress & sewing machines to poor people monthly.

BUET Rover Scout Group

Feb 2015 - Apr 2019

Activities: Volunteered on tree plantation camp & org. flood relief distribution camp monthly.

MEMBERSHIPS

Institute of Electrical and Electronics Eng. (IEEE)

American Institute of Aero and Astronautics (AIAA)

Bangladesh Astronomy Research Collaboration

- American Astronomical Society (AAS)
- **IEEE Robotics and Automation Society**
- Bangladeshi Researchers Network

REFERENCES

Dr. Benjamin Morrell

Perception Team Leader, Team CoSTAR Robotics Technologist, NASA JPL. Ex. Post Doc Researcher, JPL, Caltech. Email: benjamin.morrell@jpl.nasa.gov

Dr. Ali-Akbar Agha-Mohammadi

Team Leader, Team CoSTAR Robotics Technologist, NASA JPL.

Email: aliakbar.aghamohammadi@jpl.nasa.gov

Dr. Muhammad Abir

Thesis Co-Supervisor Adjunct. Professor, Dept. of ME, UT El Paso. Ex. Post Doc. Researcher, Dept. of NSE, MIT. Email: miabir@utep.edu

Dr. Luca Carlone

Perception Team Supervisor, Team CoSTAR Professor, Dept. of Aero Astro., MIT. Email: lcarlone@mit.edu

4 | Page